<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The planetary instrument. Or The description and use of the theories of the planets drawn in true proportion, either in one, or two plates, of eight inches diameter; by Walter Hayes, at the Cross-Daggers in Moor-Fields. Being excellent schemes ot help the conceptions of young astronomers; and ready instruments for finding the distances, longitudes, latitudes, aspects, directions, stations, and retrogradations of the planets; either mechanically, or arithmetically; with ease and speed. By Mr. John Palmer, rector of Ecton, and arch-deacon of Northampton.</title>
            <author>Palmer, John, 1612-1679.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 14 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A55074</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P249</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R38385</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99826177</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99826177</idno>
            <idno type="VID">30570</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A55074)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 30570)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1799:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The planetary instrument. Or The description and use of the theories of the planets drawn in true proportion, either in one, or two plates, of eight inches diameter; by Walter Hayes, at the Cross-Daggers in Moor-Fields. Being excellent schemes ot help the conceptions of young astronomers; and ready instruments for finding the distances, longitudes, latitudes, aspects, directions, stations, and retrogradations of the planets; either mechanically, or arithmetically; with ease and speed. By Mr. John Palmer, rector of Ecton, and arch-deacon of Northampton.</title>
                  <author>Palmer, John, 1612-1679.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>6 p., [2] leaves of plates (1 folded)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Walter Hayes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1685]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint place and date from Wing; publisher's name supplied by cataloger.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Astronomy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Astronomical instruments --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div n="2" type="plate">
            <pb facs="tcp:30570:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 31 -->
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:30570:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 30 -->
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Mars' plate</figDesc>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <head>☿</head>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1672</cell>
                           <cell>155.83.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1680</cell>
                           <cell>233.65</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>A.4</cell>
                           <cell>218.90.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1</cell>
                           <cell>53.70</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>D.1</cell>
                           <cell>4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>9.2</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Incl</cell>
                           <cell>06.54</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                     <table>
                        <head>♀</head>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1672</cell>
                           <cell>62.54.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1680</cell>
                           <cell>63.97.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>A.4</cell>
                           <cell>180.71.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1</cell>
                           <cell>224.78.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>D.1</cell>
                           <cell>1.60.2</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Incl</cell>
                           <cell>3.24.</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                     <table>
                        <head>♁</head>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1672</cell>
                           <cell>194.59.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1680</cell>
                           <cell>194.54.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>A.4</cell>
                           <cell>359.98.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>.1</cell>
                           <cell>359.75.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>D.1</cell>
                           <cell>0.98.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                     <table>
                        <head>♂</head>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1672</cell>
                           <cell>259.51.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1680</cell>
                           <cell>350.74.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>A.4</cell>
                           <cell>45.61.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1</cell>
                           <cell>191.27.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>D.1</cell>
                           <cell>0.52.4</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Incl</cell>
                           <cell>1.52.</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <byline>W: Hayes fecit.</byline>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:30570:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 32 -->
            <head>THE <hi>Planetary Inſtrument.</hi> OR THE Deſcription and Uſe of the <hi>Theories</hi> of the <hi>Planets:</hi> drawn in true <hi>Proportion,</hi> either in one, or two Plates, of eight Inches Diameter; by <hi>Walter Hayes,</hi> at the <hi>Croſs-Daggers</hi> in <hi>Moor-Fields.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">Being excellent Schemes to help the Conceptions of Young <hi>Aſtronomers;</hi> and ready Inſtruments for finding the <hi>Diſtances, Longitudes, Latitudes, Aſpects, Directions, Stations,</hi> and <hi>Retrogradations</hi> of the <hi>Planets;</hi> either <hi>Mechanically,</hi> or <hi>Arithme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tically;</hi> with Eaſe and Speed.</head>
            <byline>By Mr. <hi>John Palmer,</hi> Rector of <hi>Ecton,</hi> and Arch-Deacon of <hi>Northampton.</hi>
            </byline>
            <div type="description">
               <head>The DESCRIPTION.</head>
               <p>THE firſt Plate (which I call <hi>Saturn's</hi> Plate) contains the <hi>Theories</hi> of ♄ ♃ ♂ ♁: alſo ſhort, but ſufficient Tables of their <hi>Anomalies;</hi> and a Scale for meaſuring their Diſtances in <hi>Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diameters</hi> of the Earth.</p>
               <p>The ſecond Plate (which I call <hi>Mars</hi>'s Plate) contains the <hi>Theories</hi> of ♂ ♁ ♀ ☿, with like Tables of their <hi>Anoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies,</hi> and <hi>Scale</hi> of <hi>Diſtances.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:30570:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 33 -->
               <p>The <hi>Sun</hi> is in the Center of the <hi>Plate.</hi> The other Planets have their ſeveral <hi>Eccentrics</hi> &amp; <hi>Orbits.</hi> Theſe ſhould be <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lipſes,</hi> but <hi>Circles</hi> will ſerve ſufficiently, eſpecially for <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments.</hi> Mr. <hi>S. Foſter</hi> diſpoſed theſe <hi>Planets</hi> in four Plates, and added thereto other Devices, to be ſeen in a Book publiſhed ſince his Death. Here they are all contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in two Plates, or two ſides of one Plate: and whereas Mr. <hi>F.</hi> ſuppoſed the <hi>Apheliums</hi> and <hi>Nodes</hi> moveable, in theſe <hi>Thories</hi> they are fixed, according to Mr. <hi>Street's Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potheſis:</hi> by which means, though they be framed to the end of 1680, yet not only for this Age, but (with al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance of the Proceſſion of the <hi>Aequinoctial</hi>) they may ſerve perpetually.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Aphelium</hi> of a <hi>Planet</hi> is the point of his <hi>Eccentric,</hi> which is furtheſt from the <hi>Sun,</hi> and from <hi>Aphelium</hi> is the <hi>Anomaly</hi> counted.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Anomaly</hi> is the circular Diſtance of a <hi>Planet</hi> from his <hi>Aphelium.</hi> But though the <hi>Anomalies be equal,</hi> yet their Diviſions in every <hi>Eccentric</hi> are unequal, becauſe they are made to contain the <hi>Aggregates</hi> of the <hi>Anomalies,</hi> and <hi>Proſthaphoreſes</hi> of the <hi>Orb</hi> compounded together.</p>
               <p>Where you ſee two or three pricks on one ſide the <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit,</hi> and ☊ on the other ſide, there the <hi>Planet</hi> goes into <hi>North Latitude,</hi> and at the oppoſite Point over the <hi>Center,</hi> is the Place of ☋, where he goes into <hi>South Latitude.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="application">
               <head>The Uſe of the <hi>THEORIES.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>This ſhall be ſhewn in three <hi>Examples</hi> only, which may ſuffice.</p>
               <p>But, <hi>Note</hi> 1. That I begin the Years and Days 24 hours later than Mr. <hi>Street;</hi> for I count the laſt day of <hi>December</hi> to end in the <hi>Noon</hi> of the <hi>Circumciſion;</hi> which is the old way: and to that Account theſe <hi>Theories</hi> and <hi>Tables</hi> are fitted: and all Years and Days here are count<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Compleat.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Note</hi> 2. That in gathering the <hi>Anomalies</hi> out of the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:30570:3"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 33 -->
                  <hi>Tables,</hi> if the ſame exceed a <hi>Circle,</hi> (or 360°) you muſt by <hi>Subtraction,</hi> or <hi>Diviſion,</hi> caſt away all whole <hi>Circles,</hi> take the <hi>Remainder</hi> for the <hi>Anomaly</hi> ſought. The Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers in the <hi>Tables</hi> are <hi>Degrees,</hi> and <hi>Centeſimal</hi> parts, and for the <hi>Diurnal Motion,</hi> another <hi>Figure</hi> is added, to make the Parts <hi>Milleſimal.</hi> In the <hi>Tables,</hi> A. ſtands for <hi>Anni,</hi> that is, <hi>Years:</hi> D. ſtands for <hi>Days: Incl.</hi> ſtands for <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination;</hi> which is ſet down in <hi>Degrees</hi> and <hi>Minutes.</hi>
               </p>
               <div n="1" type="example">
                  <head>EXAMPLE. <hi>I.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>1675. <hi>April</hi> 1. I ſaw <hi>Mars</hi> above the foremoſt foot of <hi>Apollo,</hi> and he ſeemed to be much diminiſhed in Magnitude.</p>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell role="label" cols="2">Firſt out of the Table for ♁.</cell>
                           <cell role="label" cols="2">For ♂.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>write out for 1672</cell>
                           <cell>194. 59.</cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>259. 51.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell rows="2">for two Years more</cell>
                           <cell>359. 75.</cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>191. 27.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>359. 75.</cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>191. 27.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>for 90 days the product of 986 by 90 is —</cell>
                           <cell>88. 74.</cell>
                           <cell>524 in 90 —</cell>
                           <cell>47. 16.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="total">
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>1002. 83.</cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>689. 21.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>for 2 <hi>Circles</hi> deduct</cell>
                           <cell>720.</cell>
                           <cell>deduct</cell>
                           <cell>360.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="total">
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Anomaly</hi> of ♁ —</cell>
                           <cell>282. 83.</cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Anomaly</hi> of ♂</cell>
                           <cell>329. 21.</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now in the <hi>Earths Orbit,</hi> at 283, make a prick with Ink for ♁; for there is ♁ for this time: and likewiſe prick ♂ in his <hi>Orbit</hi> at 329.</p>
                  <p>Lay a Ruler from the Place of ♁ over the ☉ (in the <hi>Center</hi>) and it ſhall cut in the <hi>Limb</hi> ♈ 21° 38′, the ☉'s <hi>Longitude.</hi> Again, lay a Ruler from ♁ to ♂ (I mean, the pricks ſet for them) and know, that a Line Parallel to your <hi>Ruler,</hi> paſſing through the ☉ (or <hi>Center</hi>) will cut in the <hi>Limb</hi> the <hi>Longitude</hi> of ♂.</p>
                  <p>Take therefore with your <hi>Compaſſes</hi> the neareſt diſtance of the <hi>Center</hi> from the <hi>Ruler,</hi> and let one foot ſlide along the <hi>Ruler</hi> from ♁ to ♂, and beyond him; and let the other
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:30570:4"/>
                     <!-- PDF PAGE 34 -->foot, keeping even pace with his fellows, paſs from the <hi>Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> to the <hi>Limb,</hi> and ſo it ſhall touch in the <hi>Limb</hi> ♊ 29½, the <hi>Longitude</hi> of ♂.</p>
                  <p>Another way. Mark well the <hi>Triangle</hi> made by your two Pricks and the <hi>Center,</hi> that is, by ♁ ♂ &amp; ☉. Meaſure the ſides upon your <hi>Scale,</hi> and you ſhall find—

<table>
                        <row>
                           <cell>☉ ♁ —3500</cell>
                           <cell rows="3">
                              <hi>Semid.</hi> of ♁</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>☉ ♂ —5700</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>♁ ♂ —6000</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now if you have 2 <hi>Thrids</hi> from the <hi>Center,</hi> and lay one upon ♁, and the other upon ♂, the <hi>Arch</hi> of the <hi>Limb</hi> between them, is the Meaſure of the <hi>Angle</hi> at the ☉, (or of Commutation) and is here 77° 42′. With this <hi>Angle</hi> and the Sides comprehending it (which are 35 and 57, as before) you may by <hi>Pitiſcus</hi> his third <hi>Axiome,</hi> Calculate the other <hi>Angles,</hi> and find <hi>Ang.</hi> at ♁ (or <hi>Elongation</hi>) 67°. 41′, and <hi>Ang.</hi> at ♂ (or <hi>Paralloxis Orbis</hi>) 34° 37′. The <hi>Elongation</hi> of ♂ (67° 41′) added to the <hi>Long.</hi> of ☉ (♈ 21° 38′) makes the <hi>Long.</hi> of ♂, 89.17. that is ♊ 29.17.</p>
                  <p>Another way. Transfer your <hi>Triangle</hi> upon Paper, and there, by help of a <hi>Scale</hi> of <hi>Chords,</hi> or a ſmall <hi>Quadrant,</hi> and <hi>Compaſſes,</hi> you may eaſily find all the <hi>Angles</hi> very near the truth; <hi>Viz. Ang.</hi> ad ☉ 77° 42′. <hi>Ang.</hi> ad ♁ 67° 54′. <hi>Ang.</hi> ad ♂ 34° 24′.</p>
                  <p>Note, That the reaſon of ♂ his Diminution is the Increaſe of his Diſtance from the <hi>Earth;</hi> for you may meaſure it up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Plate 6000: but in his ☍ he may be diſtant but 1320, and never above 2350.</p>
                  <p>For the <hi>Latitude</hi> of ♂, lay one <hi>Thrid</hi> from the <hi>Center</hi> to ☊, and another <hi>Thrid</hi> to ♂, the <hi>Arch</hi> of the <hi>Limb</hi> inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted by the <hi>Thrids</hi> (76.10.) is <hi>Argumentum Latitudinis.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now as the <hi>Radius</hi> to the <hi>Tang.</hi> of 1.52′, the <hi>Inclination</hi> of ♂ : So is the <hi>Sine</hi> of 76.10′ to the <hi>Tang.</hi> of 1.49′; the <hi>North Latitude</hi> of ♂ ſeen at the <hi>Sun.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And as ♁ ♂ to ☉ ♂; ſo is the <hi>Tang.</hi> of the <hi>Lat.</hi> at the <hi>Sun,</hi> to 1. 44′; the <hi>Tang.</hi> of <hi>Lat.</hi> ſeen at the <hi>Earth.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="example">
                  <head>EXAMPLE <hi>II.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>1677. <hi>Octob.</hi> 28. (being St. <hi>Simon</hi> and <hi>Jude's.</hi>) at <hi>Noon,</hi> I ſeek ☿ Place.</p>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:30570:4"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 34 -->
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row role="label">
                           <cell cols="2">♁</cell>
                           <cell cols="2">☿</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1672. —</cell>
                           <cell>194.59</cell>
                           <cell>155.83</cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>A. 4. (or 4 Years)</cell>
                           <cell>359.98</cell>
                           <cell>218.90</cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Days 300 —</cell>
                           <cell>295.80</cell>
                           <cell>147.60</cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="total">
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>850.37</cell>
                           <cell>522.33</cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Subſtract the <hi>Circles</hi>—</cell>
                           <cell>720.</cell>
                           <cell>360.</cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Anom.</hi> of ♁</cell>
                           <cell>130.37</cell>
                           <cell>162.33.</cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Anom.</hi> of ☿</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <p>Prick the ♁ and ☿ in their <hi>Orbits,</hi> at the end of theſe <hi>Anomalies,</hi> and you ſhall ſee the Prick for ☿ fall in the very <hi>Node</hi> at ☊; and laying a <hi>Thrid,</hi> or <hi>Ruler</hi> from the <hi>Center</hi> to ☿ or ♁, it ſhall cut them both, and ſhew that ☿ is in a Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Conjunction with ☉. This ♂ ☉ ☿ would be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved: for by the help of fit <hi>Glaſſes,</hi> ☿ may be ſeen in the ☉ for ſeveral hours; and according to the beſt <hi>Tables,</hi> he ſhall paſs within 4 or 5 minutes of the ☉'s <hi>Center</hi> in <hi>North Lat.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="example">
                  <head>EXAMPLE <hi>III.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>1673. <hi>May</hi> 25. In the day time I ſaw ♀ with a <hi>Teleſcope,</hi> horned like the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> at 3 or 4 days old; and though ſhe was ſo much <hi>waned,</hi> ſhe appeared bigger and brighter than at any time ſince ſhe came laſt out of the <hi>Sun-beams.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row role="label">
                           <cell cols="2">♁</cell>
                           <cell cols="2">♀</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1672.</cell>
                           <cell>194. 59</cell>
                           <cell>62. 54</cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>144 days.</cell>
                           <cell>141. 98</cell>
                           <cell>230. 69</cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Anom.</hi> ♁</cell>
                           <cell>336. 57</cell>
                           <cell>293. 23</cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Anom.</hi> ♀.</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <p>Prick theſe <hi>Planets</hi> in their <hi>Anomalies,</hi> as before was taught, Lay a <hi>Ruler</hi> from ♁ over the <hi>Center,</hi> and it ſhall cut in the <hi>Limb</hi> the <hi>Long.</hi> of the ☉, II 14.11′. The <hi>Ruler</hi> thus lying, draw a <hi>Thrid</hi> from the <hi>Center</hi> over ♀. Now between the <hi>Ruler</hi> and the <hi>Thrid</hi> is the <hi>Angle</hi> of <hi>Commutation</hi> (163°) and there adjoyneth to it the <hi>Supplement</hi> thereof (17°) which in your <hi>Triangle</hi> is <hi>Angulus ad</hi> ☉, and is meaſured by the <hi>Limb.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Lay your <hi>Ruler</hi> from ♁ to ♀, and the <hi>Parallel Line</hi> made,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:30570:5"/>
                     <!-- PDF PAGE 35 -->
or imagined to be made, with your <hi>Compaſſes</hi> through the <hi>Center,</hi> will cut ♋ 17°; the <hi>Long.</hi> of ♀, and the <hi>Arch</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween this and the ☉'<hi>s</hi> Place before found, is the <hi>Elongation</hi> of ♀ from ☉ <hi>Eaſtwards,</hi> 32.49′. And the Summe of the <hi>Commutation</hi> and <hi>Elongation</hi> taken out of 180, leaves the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle</hi> at ♀ 130.11.</p>
                  <p>Another way. In the <hi>Triangle</hi> ♁ ♀ ☉, you may take all the ſides in your <hi>Compaſſes,</hi> and meaſure them upon the <hi>Scale,</hi> that is, ☉ ♁ 3520. ☉ ♀ 2450, and ♁ ♀ 1370. Then either by <hi>Protraction</hi> find the <hi>Angles:</hi> or, the <hi>Angle</hi> of <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutation</hi> being known (17°) and the ſides including by <hi>Ax.</hi> 3. <hi>Pitiſci,</hi> you may compute the <hi>Angle</hi> at the ♁ 32.49 and the <hi>Angle</hi> at ♀ 130.11.</p>
                  <p>This <hi>Angle</hi> at ♀ meaſureth her <hi>Waxing</hi> and <hi>Waning.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Let the <hi>Radius</hi> be 100, the <hi>Diameter</hi> of ♀ 200, the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle</hi> being 130.11′, the verſed <hi>Sine</hi> thereof (165) meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the dark part of the <hi>Diameter;</hi> the reſidue (35) is light: So ♀ is <hi>Waned</hi> 165/200 of her <hi>Diameter;</hi> that is almoſt 10 <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gits;</hi> and yet ſhe ſeems much bigger than when ſhe was <hi>Full:</hi> becauſe 2 <hi>Digits</hi> of light in her preſent Diſtance (of 1370) contain more <hi>Seconds</hi> of light than her full <hi>Disk</hi> could con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain; when coming from the ☉, ſhe was diſtant about 6000, as you may meaſure upon the <hi>Plate.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <p>How theſe <hi>Plates</hi> may be alſo uſeful for Obſerving <hi>Alti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes, Azimuths, Declinations,</hi> and <hi>Inclinations</hi> of <hi>Plains,</hi> &amp;c. They who have any Skill in the <hi>Mathematicks,</hi> may eaſily diſcern without further Admonition.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:30570:5"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:30570:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 36 -->
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div n="1" type="plate">
            <pb facs="tcp:30570:6"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 36 -->
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Saturn's plate</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
